Hello, and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going to
be looking at the hydrogenation of lipids.
Meaning that whenever we have
a really big fat, sometimes
you'll have unsaturated fats.
So this is something that occurs,
that occurs artificially when you
kind of want to buy different things
that you find in the grocery store.
If you read a lot of those different
labels, you'll see that it might
say that it's hydrogenated on it.
This is a reaction that occurs to
help extend the shelf life of a lot
of the different things that you
commonly find in your grocery store.
Um, this also helps create a lot of the
different things that we use on a regular
basis for baking and things like that.
So it transforms the fats so it gets rid
of, um, not having as many unsaturated
fats in your diet, but it gets rid of also
the possibility of having cholesterol and
things like that in those fats as well.
So there's kind of like a hit or miss,
like sure you have more saturated fats.
But, this is something that extends
shelf life, um, in a lot of your foods.
So what it is, just to go through
the definition, is hydrogenation
is when we take hydrogen gas and
we bubble it through a heated oil.
So if you have like an oil in your
stove, you heat it up really hot, what
they do is they bubble hydrogen through
it in the presence of a catalyst.
Usually this is like, uh, usually
nickel, for example, being that it's
usually a little cheaper to use.
So, when they do this in industry,
they will take an unsaturated fat,
which is typically a liquid or
something that's like a little goopy,
and when you add a hydrogen to it,
it's going to remove the double bonds
and turn them into single bonds.
So if you kind of think back to my
previous videos on organic when it came
to addition reactions It's like if we had
the double bond Which is like are my two
parts of my hand here and we're going to
be opening up that double bond, right?
We're opening up the doors Now,
when you're doing that, you're
going to be adding hydrogen
to each of those little bits.
Okay.
So let's take a look at this reaction
and try to see what it's all about.
All right.
So with the reaction, what it's,
what we're going to have here is
we have an unsaturated fat and I
highlighted the double bonds here
in green and what we're going to be
doing is adding hydrogen to them.
So like I said before, it's as if we're
going to be opening up the double doors.
So if I change one of these double
bonds to blue here, we're going to
be opening it up just like you're
opening up a cabinet in your house.
So if I were to do that, we're
going to open up that double
bond on each of these structures.
And as a result, we're going to be
adding hydrogen to each one, all right?
So being that we have our hydrogen
under a nickel catalyst right here,
this is the idea of the reaction.
So, but before we do that,
we want to illustrate that
this is a complete reaction.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to copy and paste
our structure here, right?
And sadly, if you're using a
notebook, you got to write it twice.
That's the hardest part, but write them
as condensed structures, that makes
it a lot easier when doing lipids,
because geometric is a little long.
Remember, these types of molecules
are generally 12 to 18 or more carbons
long, they're very difficult to always
draw, so make it easy on yourself.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to open up that double bond.
So just to illustrate the first one,
right, we added hydrogen to each one.
Now what can you generally do instead?
Well, you can just write H2
on each of these, just like
this, and erase your bond.
Now is this kind of the
best way to do that though?
This is a condensed structure.
So we're adding hydrogen to each, but
keep in mind that these structures
here are all about, and I realized
I forgot some twos here, is that we
have a condensed structure, meaning we
can use subscripts to minimize these.
So what we will do is instead is kind
of count how many hydrogens there are.
So we're kind of showing our work,
or how many carbons you have.
So in the middle here, we have one, two
carbons, and then another set of CH2s.
So we have seven of them next to it.
So we have a total of nine
CH2s they're going to make.
Over on our left hand side,
we also have seven CH2s, so
we'll add them all together.
So if we kind of count, right,
we have seven plus seven plus
two, so that's sixteen total.
So what we are going to do is kind
of erase this all here in the middle,
and we are going to make it so that
our CH2s will now say sixteen, because
we're counting all of our carbons,
and then we'll move over our CH3s.
So this would be our
final answer down here.
So notice how by hydrogenating it, it
all gets nice and clumped together as
one little nice little solid is kind of
how I like to think about that, right?
Because when it's saturated, this
is going to be a solid as a result.
Okay, so we have a saturated,
so those are all single bonds
versus when we started, right?
There were double bonds
or unsaturated fat.
And that's the whole idea, is that
you're opening up those double bonds.
And now this can be done not just with
hydrogenation, it can be done with
bromination, hydrohalogenation, any of the
addition reactions can be done with this.
And if you need a little refresher on
addition reactions, go refer back to
my video on addition reactions too.
I hope that this video helped to
shorten and sweeten to the point.
And if you want to see future
videos, please like, like, subscribe,
comment, let me know what you think,
and I'd be happy to make more.
Alright, I'll see you all later, and
I hope you all have a wonderful day.
Bye now.